The result of these considerations was a module written for 3D Slicer (www.slicer.org). The module finds the landmarks which the atlas model and patient data have in common, and for each common point (in both sets), another fiducial is added at an offset normal to the curvature of the spine. The direction normal to the curvature of the spine was computed using the cross products of the appropriate landmark-to-landmark vectors around the landmark being duplicated. A Right-Left (R-L) vector was constructed from points on opposite transverse processes of a given vertebra. When a vertebra was in between two other vertebrae with landmarks, a Superior-Inferior (S-I) vector was computed as the average of the vector to the point being duplicated from the inferior neighbor, and the vector from this point to the superior neighbor. When a point only had one neighbor above or below it, this average resulted from a single vector. 
The offset distance was chosen to be a constant 30mm for the atlas spine’s landmarks. Length scale variation was taken into account by multiplying this 30mm by the ratio of the length of the patient’s spine to that of the atlas model. The lengths of both spines were computed using the sum of the distances from each point to its inferior neighbor, and averaged across the right and left sides so that curvature would not skew the length.
For example, in Figure 1, the location of T6L’ was computed as:
T6L^'=T6L+(30mm∙(L_P÷L_A ))∙[((T5L-T7L)÷2)×(T6R-T6L)]÷|[((T5L-T7L)÷2)×(T6R-T6L)]|
Where boldface indicates a vector representation of the point’s location, LP is the length of the patient’s spine model, LA is the length of the atlas spine, • represents scalar multiplication, × is the vector cross-product, and │v│ is the length of vector v. This formula was modified as needed for the superior-most and inferior-most points, as they had only one inferior/superior neighbor from which to compute the S-I vector. The order of the cross product was also reversed for the right sided points, so that the offsets were still into the anterior direction. 
